Curriculum Vitae Christoph Bamberg

Profile

I am a doctorate researcher at the Eating Behaviour Lab Salzburg where I investigate how Intermittent fasting affects us individually. I am continuing work that I started at the University of Auckland and Maastricht University. My passion is to find new ways to understand and describe human behaviour. I am intensely studying Bayesian statistics, Machine Learning tools and am excited about open science practices. I enjoy analysing data as much as coming up with creative research questions.

Work Experience

DOCTORATE RESEARCHER | EATING BEHAVIOUR LAB, PARIS LODRON UNIVERSITY, SALZBURG, AT | SINCE 10.2022

- Developing a controlled, longitudinal, high sampling experiment on the effects of Intermittent Fasting on cognitive performance, mood and body. Using smartphone and behavioural data.
- Conducting a systematic review and meta-analysis (cooperation with University of Auckland, NZ)
- Contributed to a many-analysts project for the standardisation of EEG analyses
- Conducting an online A/B-test measuring effects of hunger and subjective expectations on concentration (cooperation with University of Maastricht, NL)

RESEARCHER | TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DORTMUND, GER | 11.2019 - 05.2021

- ► Conducted an fMRI study on extinction learning in adolescence
- Designed a novel experimental paradigm for an online study on cognitive flexibility across different ages
- Collected, analysed and presented the results of the online study
- Supervised and guided two student assistants, an intern, a bachelor and master thesis

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | RUHR UNIVERSITY BOCHUM | 03.2018 -03.2019

- Assisted in a study on the effects of hypnotic suggestions on tactile acuity and associated neural representations
- Performed and analysed EEG measurements of resting state and somatosensory evoked potentials

Education

M.SC. COGNITIVE SCIENCE | RUHR UNIVERSITY BOCHUM, GER | 10.2017 - 10.2019

- ► Final grade: 1.2 (first class honours degree)
- Researched the effects of fasting on social behaviour and the brain using EEG
- ▶ Helped standardising the EEG analysis pipelines at the University clinic.
- Courses included cognitive science, psychology, neuropsychology, psychiatry, research methods (EEG, fMRI), philosophy of mind, philosophy of science
- Summer School for Analysing Neural Time Series Data (Radboud University, NL): Studied mathematical foundations of time frequency analysis, Fourier transformation, simulating data

B.A. PHILOSOPHY & ECONOMICS | UNIVERSITY OF BAYREUTH, GER | 10.2013 - 04.2017

- ► Final grade: 2.0 (upper second class honours degree)
- ▶ Bachelor thesis on explanations of behaviour in the Wason Selection Task.
- ► Courses included logic, statistics, theory of science, decision theory, economics
- Spent one semester in Estonia, studying at the Tallinn University of Technology

Skills

- Statistical analysis and visualisation with R and Python
- Querying relational databases with MySQL
- Functional programming in Python
- ► EEG and fMRI data analysis with Python and Matlab
- Developing behavioural research paradigms with Psychopy (Python)
- Systematic literature search and review

Funding and Prizes

- ► Scholarship for the promotion of scientific theses. Paris Lodron University Salzburg.
- Two poster prizes for scientific presentations
- 4th place Creative Shock Business Case Competition in Vilnius, Lithuania, 2014

Further Work and Teaching

FREELANCE DATA SCIENTIST AND STATISTICS TUTOR | 04.2022 - PRESENT

- Over 20 clients through fiverr and word-of-mouth from psychology, economics and medicine
- Gaining hands-on experience in client-communication, project work and a variety of data sets

LEARNING BAYESIAN STATISTICS PODCAST | 04.2022 - PRESENT

- Promoting the podcast on social media, cutting interesting sound snippets and creating abstracts
- Writing and publishing newsletter for listeners
- Hosting webinars
- https://learnbayesstats.com/

LECTURER | PARIS LODRON UNIVERSITY | 04.2023 - 08.2023

• Graduate level seminar for practical research skills, supervising students in their projects, teaching programming skills

GUEST LECTURER | UNIVERSITY OF BAYREUTH | 04.2019

- Guest lecturer for an undergraduate level block seminar with 18 students
- Seminar introduced students to research in cognitive science, philosophy of mind and neuroscience

TUTOR | RUHR UNIVERSITY BOCHUM | 09.2018 - 03.2019

▶ Tutor for logic and theory of science accompanying a graduate level lecture

Voluntary work and outreach

LANGUAGE CAFÉ FOR UKRAINIAN COMMUNITY | SALZBURG | 05.2023 - PRESENT

▶ Helping Ukrainian refugees improve their German skills

PINT OF SCIENCE FESTIVAL | 05.2022

- Organising and hosting a science festival to promote local science
- https://pintofscience.at/team/Salzburg

TEACHER AT SUMMERSCHOOL | LEUPHANA SUMMER ACADEMY | 08.2017 - 09.2017

- Summer school for students from less privileged backgrounds, preparing them for their graduation
- Tutored students in mathematics and presentation skills, helped them find an apprenticeship

MENTORSHIP PROGRAMS | BOCHUM & DORTMUND, GER | 04.2018 - 01.2021

- Helped international students arriving in Bochum to integrate and manage bureaucratic affairs
- ► Established friendships in 1:1 tandem partnership with a person with immigration background

DEVELOPMENT AID VOLUNTEERING | LIUKU, YUNNAN, CHINA | 09.2012 - 10.2013

- ► Taught English at a rural middle school
- Cared for children in need and people affected by civil war
- Organised and held hygiene training courses and used cloth collections
- Established a godparent program that enabled children to visit primary school